嗯。
喺。
梁先生，歡迎咁多位。
好，或者我哋請有關嘅。
推出夠時間，我哋一開始好嗎？
依都提大家咧，就誒。
我哋都呢個時候等我哋嘅工作人士入場。
誒背景資料嘅話咧，我哋可以馬上開始請我哋誒有關嘅。
一號嘅就係變誒廣東話嘅版本咧，二號英文版本咧，而三號係普通話版本嘅。
議會人士參與先，包括我哋政府嘅誒代表同埋有關嘅公眾人士先入場。
誒誒，發現嘅話咧，大家可以用翻我哋嘅誒嘅耳筒啦，包括係一號。
誒，公眾人士開始發言先。首先，我哋請咧就第三位，應該就係律師會嘅，本來係。
大家出席，我哋呢個誒發言咧係並不受到特權法嘅保障嘅。亦都希望提大家睇睇關我哋關於公眾人士嘅需知咧喺枱面上會有㗎啦。咁亦冇其他嘅。
係我哋歡迎我哋政府嘅代表，今日有我哋嘅教育局嘅副局長蔡若蓮博士咧，有首席嘅助理秘書長陳武銀女士，誒，另外一位助理秘書長係課程課程發展嘅李沙倫先生咧，誒，關於幼專教嘅李月周若蘭女士咧，同埋關於高級教育主任係啊何任。
係。
最近。
嗯。
誒對唔住啊！
多謝主席。誒。
提供多啲資源，特別誒喺而家幼幼兒教育底下，其實誒。
安排座位上有少少唔同咗，因為本來應該係律師會嘅林露西女士嘅。誒，我代黃石紅女士嘅。
得我係四號啊！哦，得好啊，對唔住啊，我對唔住，對唔住，係請張茂清先生先好嘛，唔該你。O K。
當佢哋即使係佢哋有大專學歷，但係中文嘅應用水平不足夠嘅底下咧，佢哋去到尋找工作，誒好多僱主都會拒步，誒亦都好難去揾到一啲誒真係可以應用到佢哋專業，就係因為佢哋嘅中文能力。
睇嚟，大家咧，我哋今日嘅文件咧，包括係立法會嘅政府嘅文件咧，係編號九零九sh七十八零一號啦，同埋立法會秘書處而備嘅文件係關於資料介背景資料介紹嘅，係九二一sh七十八零一文件嘅。歡迎多位公眾人士嚇，噉就睇睇大家咧。你如果想聽到我哋嘅現場嘅。
O.K.啦嘛，係張先生，係誒今日誒主要講翻少數族裔教育問題啦。咁其實我哋知道而家面對緊少數族裔咧，誒喺幼兒教育、中學甚至小學一直以嚟咧，誒對於佢哋嚟講嘅中文支援其實係唔足夠嘅，令到佢哋其實好多時咧，而家就算係誒嚟咗香港兩代、三代。
甚至而家嚟緊第四代，誒面對住嘅問題係佢進入到社會度，甚至入到去間茶餐廳望到份餐牌，佢都睇唔明，更加唔識講要嗌啲乜嘢食啲乜嘢。呢個係一個好嚴峻嘅問題嚟嘅。誒，更加地係佢哋誒進入到社會入邊，相需要進入揾工作嘅時候。
不足以融入到社會，咁呢個係好嚴峻嘅問題。誒當然誒好多不誒不少嘅小數族裔，其實誒擁有誒好強嘅學習能力啦，誒接受到大專教育，但係正正就係因為中文嘅問題，令到佢哋進入社會、融入社會誒變成一種困礙。所以誒，我哋而家喺度其實希望誒各方。
誒去嚴峻去諗一諗，其實應該點樣去支援呢班小語族裔？誒，正如誒之前所公佈嘅誒中中文為中國語文為第二語言個個框架啦。其實我哋認為嚴重係即係未能夠可以完全協助到班小語族裔學生去。
學習到中文，特別喺喺誒幼兒教育方面，其實各方應該諗多啲方法去著手喺嗰段學習語言嘅黃金期嗰度，點樣可以喺嗰個時間框架入邊，可以幫助到嗰班小眾嘅學童，真正可以接受到中文誒語境、語意又好，所有嘅誒詞彙。
誒協助到佢哋進入翻一個主流理論上應該誒以中文為母語嘅學生誒，你唔好話真係要睇齊啦。咁但係起碼都要令到佢哋誒正常溝通、閲讀、誒睇睇文件，都起碼係有能力嘅處理呢件事情。誒嗰段黃金期，希望各方。
誒局方畀嘅支援，無論係教師、學校，其實都係嚴重不足夠㗎。所以希望誒局方都可以提供多啲資源擺落去誒統一研究一套框架擺落去幼兒教育嗰一度，無論去協助到幼稚園、協助到教師減輕佢哋負擔又好，誒都需要有一套統一啲嘅框架貼。
中文基礎嘅。
We now invite Ms. Labour Cetek of the We Super Women Group, please.
有一一定比例嘅教師咧，完成一啲基礎或者高級嘅誒課程嘅。咁多謝各位。唔該曬。
Hi, I'm Liba. Currently studying Dealey Memorial School Broadway, and my family they applied for the scheme in two thousand fifteen.
語生咧有兩萬小時嘅聽説中文嘅一個經驗差距，咁其實非華語生咧，佢哋係欠缺咧華語生咧，由佢哋一齣世開始咧喺屋企嗰個聽説中文嗰個誒學習嘅機會，亦都亦都係我哋叫做一個習得嘅機會啦。
咁咧，而事實上咧，前線嘅經驗都話畀我哋聽咧，非華語生咧好多時係因為語言嘅障礙咧，咁而誒學習受阻嘅。即係例如咧，誒好多華語生咧已經能夠舉手答老師問題嘅時候咧，其實非華語生咧仲喺度聽緊咧。
做到佢哋點樣去教導呢班少數族裔學生，而以免誒我哋接受到我哋情況，其實係佢哋甚至係會用英文去教導呢班少數族裔學生，其實根本接觸唔到中文嘅。所以誒，暫時係咁多，多謝主席。唔該曬張生，跟住我哋請阿林老西女士。
咁誒，根據咧我哋誒，即係誒我哋前線嘅一啲工作嘅經驗咧，噉我哋有幾點嘅倡議嘅。咁誒，第一咧就係我哋希望教育局咧係可以提誒提供一啲咧誒增潤式嘅中文學習時段畀幼稚園嘅學生，咁補足佢哋嘅中文嘅落後啦。
咁誒，亦都有啲誒個人同埋二人嘅小組學習時間啦。咁亦都咧，我哋係發展咗一套咧，為非華語幼兒而設咧，亦都適用於全港幼稚園嘅中文作為第二語言嘅課程教材、教學法同埋評估工具嘅。咁誒喺統計學上面咧，我哋嗰個成效咧都係非常之顯著嘅。
誒大家好，我係樂小慧嘅代表。誒，我哋今次嚟咧係希望提出咧，而家政府咧係非華語學生嘅教育政策上咧有一個好重大缺口，亦都係剛才呢位先生講咧，就係學前教育。噉我哋期望咧教育局咧盡快增撥資源咧，由呢個幼兒嘅語語言黃金期入手咧，為非華語生咧打開一個。
咁誒，我哋知道咧，誒有好多普遍大眾咧，佢哋以為咧，誒非華語生佢哋入讀本地幼稚園咧，就可以同非華語生一樣咧，順利咁學習中文。咁但係其實咧，研究清楚顯示咧，誒非華語生咧，其實佢哋係一個中文嘅第二語言學習者啦。其實佢哋入幼稚園嘅時候咧，已經同華
老師究竟係講緊啲乜嘢？噉佢哋好多時咧就會成為班上面嘅沉默者啦，或者咧畀人以為佢係行為情緒有問題啦，甚至一啲好難搞嘅學生。咁所以咧，我哋覺得咧，即係誒呢一度咧係好多時咧會影響到佢哋吸收其他學科嘅知識咧，同埋學習進度都係好滯後嘅。咁其實咧，誒面對呢個政策嘅不足咧，誒。
我哋樂師會咧喺二零一五年咧已經開始咧，由同香港大學啦，同埋香港教育大學咧有一個叫做從起步開始幼稚園非華語學生學習中文支援計劃嘅咁呢個計劃咧。其實我哋就係誒有六間嘅project school啦，咁其實就係提供緊一啲誒互動嘅增潤嘅中文課程畀非華語嘅幼兒。
and。
The complicated process.
like manage in one salary。
and it was really hard for us to.
And we did not know about the scheme when I was in primary school.
但係，我哋都係因為語言障礙，和
earning in our family and we are six members in a family. I have three more siblings younger than me.
我同意，有些學校，佢哋畀信息和通知，係related to the scheme，但係，啲信息係唔夠。
我 want to request that it will be great if there is a specific form filling services for ethnic minorities.
我母用嚟畀他們packed milk，一或二次，only，他們會often會病，因為那milk唔適合他們。
my question is those ethnic minorities who do not know about any NGOs in Hong Kong, how are they going to apply for the scheme?
my mother even did not use disposable diapers for them. My family spend less on food and we eat meat occasionally.
then my mother came to know about the Catholic Workers Centre from a friend and they it's an NGO and they helped us with the form filling and they told us about the scheme.
It would be more helpful if IDB and SFA employ local ethnic minority staff who can help not only to publicise the scheme but also to help throughout the application of SFA.
my other two siblings, younger ones, my parents stopped giving them formula milk because they they were just one years one year old, because formula milk is very expensive, and my family can't afford to buy it.
咁第二咧就係誒，我哋希望教育局咧可以好似小學階段噉樣咧，喺幼稚園階段咧誒提供一個中文作為第二語言嘅增潤課程，作為一個補充嘅指引。咁第三咧就係誒，其實教育局咧由一七一八今年學年開始咧，就為誒取錄百名以上嘅非華語幼兒嘅幼稚園咧提供。
冇一個額外嘅資助嘅噉，但係咧，其實咧係有誒三百一十四間，相等於咧五十四個percent嘅誒收取非華語生嘅幼轉嘅幼轉裏邊嘅一批嘅幼稚園咧，其實佢哋係冇任何資助嘅。誒係咪係好快講完啊？咁咧誒呢批小朋友咧就係即係誒冇任何資助，但係其實佢哋學中文。
咧係唔比其他嘅誒非華語生係容易嘅咁誒。第四咧就係咧誒，我哋希望咧誒教育局都可以咧，好似參照誒S.E.N.嗰個誒專業發展教教師專業發展嗰個framework噉樣咧，就係誒規即係誒規範咧。幼兒園老師咧，可能例如喺五年之內咧係接受一定誒有一定程度。
And my primary school, they never mention about the scheme, nor did they give the information for the about the scheme. It was really hard for my family to manage for the book fees and other related expenses, because my father is the only one.
嗯。
primary and secondary school level proactively.
We can get better education only if we are economically satisfied. Thank you.
兩 jobs or long working hours in order to survive with all those educational expenses.
我 want to insist ADB to promote student finance schemes on kindergarten.
Thank you, Ms. Vic. We now invite Ms. Aupsema of the Catholic Workers' Centre, please.
SFA in different EM languages, so most of the authentic minorities may not even know about.
and some parents they don't there's leaflets for the scheme but some parents they don't even receive the leaflets.
secondly，those parents whose children are studying in kindergarten，they don't even know about free mission scheme and recent KJ grant。
學校應該被給明確的指引，來協助EM家長申請SFS方案，和經過整個程序。謝謝。
The situation is even worse for kindergarten. That fee remission scheme will be put in veil from parents till some parents luckily get information from outside.
and it would be great if EDB and SFA can collaborate with schools to arrange form-filling sessions and talks or maybe seminars about SFA.
from form-filling session should be arranged in the cooperation with school during application period. EM inquiry hotlines should be arranged for parents for inquire about their application.
學生 finance 計畫，There is no introduction seminars or promotional activities are arranged by the school or EDB. The second step, if I talk about those parents who know about student finance but they do not know how to apply.
Hi, I'm here to represent and talk on the behalf of my group member. I want to focus more about support measures provided by EDB and schools to apply for student financial assistance schemes for primary and secondary school students. There are there is no leaflets available.
所以，我認為。
We now have Ms. Louisa Castro, please.
家庭去完成申請forms。Thank you。Thank you，Ms. Sarah。
and how to fill up the forms and or go through the procedures. No assistant is available for EDB or school. Parents are left helpless. They suffer a lot without applying those assistance schemes. They need to borrow money from friends, spend less on food on other basic needs. Husbands need to do.
多謝。我們現在有Mrs. Abas Saira of the Catholic Diocese of the Hong Kong Diocesan Pastoral Centre of Workers' Council。多謝主席。其實我亦都想聚焦學生 finance 計畫可達性，對於 EM 家庭。在 2017-18 學年開始，我們有研究。
Which findings were released in November 2017? The research shows that the interviewees' proficiency in Chinese and English language is not high. Only 59.4% can read and 50.9% can write English. With their Chinese reading and writing abilities are lower.
到10%。Actually，therefore，they，really，need，leaflets，or，brochures，in，English，or，even，in，their，mother，languages，in，order，to，know，the，financial，schemes，provided，by，the，government。Although，the，EDB，has，published，household，application，for，student，finance，assistance，schemes，leaflets，in，Chinese，and，English，and，were，translated。
into six EM languages too, but it is pity that they are only available for collection at SFA centre. Among interviewees, only sixty point sixty five seven of them had the leaflets in English distributed to them by school. Only five point three of them obtained.
leaflet in their first language from the school. Other than this, the research also reveals that 80% of the respondents expressed that they encountered difficulties during the application. These difficulties include their illiteracy in Chinese and English. That was 63.3%. And then.
for the compli complicated process, it was fifty six point seven percent, and their inability to communicate with staff of the student finance assistance centre is forty five point six percent. even though even though these difficulties, only twenty point twenty two point two percent of SFAF.
申請者Approach the school for help. Seventy-four point three of the applicants who had not seek any help from their schools were not aware that school can help them. Thirty-five point seven per cent of them could not communicate with school, so they did not ask for any help from school. Only thirty.
百分之十的respondents who received assistance from schools， they said that schools' assistance was helpful。 in the second part of research， we contacted forty eight schools where quite number of EM children are studying。 only eight out of forty eight schools said that they have EM language leaflet。 we have a case of。
作為。
two zero zero nine。
endorment fund，the land premium was paid。
是目前在在process of con
stated in the previous deputation that the United Muslim Association.
Okay, thank you, Chairman. My name is Ahmed Rohil and I'm Chairman of United Muslim Association of Hong Kong.
The memorandum of agreement that was signed with the Ministry of Finance of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia in 13 September.
after the after the late King Abdullah tried to finance the construction project is on hold since July 2016.
We reiterate that Hong Kong is our home and request the Hong Kong government to help us to make it a viable home for our community. Thank you very much. Thank you, Mr. Castro. Next, we have Mr. Ahmed Raheel of the United Muslim Association of Hong Kong, please.
和傳達我們的 urgent plea to the SAR government to provide assistance for us to realise our decades-long dream of providing not only a place of worship, but also a range of community services for our youth as well as the elderly.
The lease premium of 9.35 million to construct an Islamic centre and a 2,000-bed elderly care home through the generous grant of Qatar.
Construction the Shinshui Mos Islamic Centre and Elderly Home Project. The plot of land is 2,046 square metre. Was acquired in Shinshui in 2006 with.
ethnic minority families whose son need to do full time security job at night in order to maintain family's expenses because they don't know how to apply for student finance assistance. When they approach us, it was already that child was already in secondary five. In the since primary, they never apply for student fin.
EDB should provide schools with household application for student financial assistance schemes leaflets and the template of application forms in six EM language. EDB should employ EM ambassador to help publicise the student finance schemes and also EDB should cooperate with schools to help parents of EM.
Thank you, Chairman. I would like to represent the United Muslim Association for Hong Kong, and I would like to raise the following points. As per the minutes of the previous meeting, we requested that a new mosque should be built in the new territories with government assistance, and that it should not be tied up with a social service facility, as our community is unable to.
finance such a large project, and in reality, the Hong Kong SAR government is well equipped to construct such facilities. In fact, nearby religious groups in other districts have monasteries, churches, granted land without such a requirement, and we only request for a similar condition considering the increase in worshippers living in the new territories. Furthermore,
We were not allowed to establish a secondary school when other religious and non-religious groups have been granted and assisted by the government through the years. I've submitted the information, and some years after Umm's application for an international secondary school, the SAR government proceeded to grant other schools space funding in two thousand.
在九，。
Our land grant is subject to a high premium and granting of land still facing penalty, and we would like to request that this penalty and premium be waived. Our chairman pointed out previously that the regrant premium for the headquarters of the Hong Yi Kok Rural Council was only 1,000, and this is in the Legislative Council minutes in.
六December two thousand and one. Even though some of its facilities, such as the theatre, exhibition hall, conference room, can be hired by the public and they make a profit from such activities. Legislative minutes also show that in two thousand and six, the government required an elderly home in nearby Sai Kung Lung Ho Hau Wan to pay a premium of only one thousand, and that is all.
所以，在十二月二零零一年，變異的價格在相似的申請是顯著的政府偏見和歧視的證據。我們敬請委員會審查我們的項目，允許我們改變社會服務的性質，在使用這塊土地時提供，包括一個為民族少數族裔的培訓中心。
The mosque part.
100年喺香港。
which may be interested in.
Fund of Elderly Home，Pending Out Funding for。
and still we don't have one centre for help the minority.
and because the minority is more is living more than
for your information， we already running at one elderly home in Thin Moon。
We have continually approached various institutions, one of which is Jockey Club Trust.
Thank you, Ms. Rayhill。誒，跟住我哋有請誒卓文寶小姐，係Society of Community Integration。好多謝主席。
喺中學學嘅中文咧，比起小學學嘅中文程度仲要淺嘅。原因係咩咧？就係因為原來而家學校究竟教少數族裔中文嘅程度，其實係base誒基於老師覺得佢哋嘅程度去到邊。
This has been a continued struggle for our community to realise this project, and despite all of difficulties, external and internal, we we remain stand fast.
And also one Islamic primary school in Yulong, and one is a madrissa where we teach Islamic teaching, and also like an information centre.
當沙特公使在香港 send 一 letter  to the government of Hong Kong SAR that they want to postpone the project of the same time. We are awaiting their final decision at the end of February. Whatever they will continue with the project.
學習一直都停留喺好低嘅階段。
誒去access到呢一啲噉樣嘅information啦，咁同埋咧係誒。
所以我哋覺得咧，其實強而有力嘅質素保證啦、監督啦、同埋評估以及問責嘅機制咧，係對於
嗱，其實唔係㗎嘛，所以呢個做法淨係喺小數族裔學中文嗰度發生咧，我哋發覺係好唔合理嘅，所以應該係要有一個階段學習目標。
學習材料，噉我就想問，其實點解係唔同嘅院校發展唔同嘅教材？究竟教材之間係咪有協調嘅咧？點解嗰個考慮唔係發展一個真係由小一去到小六，等本地嘅小到中嘅學生可以循序漸進咁學，學到一個程度係可以融入翻主流課堂嘅咧？
係為咗確保所有嘅非華語學生咧，同埋非華同埋華語嘅學生咧，可以同齊享有同等學習中文嘅機會，同埋咧係要建構一個共融嘅校園，而且咧誒喺呢一個誒誒政策下邊咧係講咗唔要一個誒越教淺嘅一個誒中文課程嘅。
我 still， you know this this community centre is very important for us. Otherwise, you know we will we will going all around same as again the story that we don't have any communication places or like that. So this this centre is very important. So the government should help this project. Thank you very much.
主席啊，其實有好多小數族裔嚟揾我哋嘅時候咧，我哋發覺就算係土生土長大嘅學生，如果佢由幼稚園開始讀中文，小學讀中文學校，如果佢去到中學嘅時候入咗一啲小數族裔好多嘅學校咧，原來學校教嘅中文程度咧係唔係一定令佢有進步㗎？有啲小數族裔嘅學生發覺原來佢中文，
咁所以咧，其實我哋一直覺得要有一個階段性嘅學習目標，就係講緊如果係小數字嘅學生土生土長學中文嘅，究竟去到咩年級應該學到咩，去到邊度？呢個應該有一個清晰嘅指引，唔係老師自己決定覺得佢要學深啲，定係覺得佢要學淺啲。因為而家嘅問題就係好多老師對佢哋嘅期望唔高，所以令到佢哋嘅中
今次我哋見到教育局嘅文言咧，又講過佢話係基於小數族裔學生嘅語言文化差異同埋學習中文嘅年期唔同，所以唔可以設立呢個階段學習目標。但係我哋發現呢個講法其實係奇怪嘅，因為就算係主流嘅華裔學生都好咧，其實佢哋學英文嘅年期都可以唔一樣，或者佢哋嘅。
起步點都可以唔同㗎，但係如果係一班裏邊有一啲學生嘅英文水平比較差咧，其實老師嘅做法咪會畀一啲補課佢啊，一啲補習佢啊，幫佢嘅成績拉高。然後到最後佢哋都係擺翻喺同一班㗎嘛，而唔係見到佢哋餵你英文程度好低，噉我就將你拉出嚟放去第二班淺啲嘅英文啊，英文班。
然後咧，其實而家我哋一直覺得學校裏邊係好老師，其實一直都好無助，唔知點樣教先好冇適當嘅教學材料。今次我哋見到教育局嘅文件咧，就有講佢有委託一個高等院校發展小一至小三嘅教學材料啦，然後又委託另一間高等院校發展小三至小四嘅。
最後，我哋就想講一個關於選校嘅問題，因為咧，我發覺原來之前用樂會做咗一個研究，就係講緊，就算教育局有畀撥款畀學校進行一啲非華語學生嘅中文支援都好咧，有攞錢嘅學校唔一定要將啲支援措施擺喺學校概覽嘅。今次我就見到教育局嘅文件咧有寫。
説話其實佢哋而家已經叫哈家校合作社考慮緊以劃一嘅形式喺學生支援一欄內，即係喺學校概覽裏邊啦，以劃一嘅形式指出學校為非華語學生做出製做嘅一啲支援措施。咁所以我就想教育局喺呢度可以澄清一下，究竟呢個劃一嘅形式，只不過係喺現有嘅學校。
Thank you very much.
and until now, they still hesitate to speak Chinese.
Now to really help us, we want to have.
That my kids don't have enough confidence to speak Chinese.
Now I feel that learning Chinese is equally important in our daily life or at work.
唔該，主席。唔該，張小姐。誒，Next，could we invite Ms. Fabiola Reyes，please？
我認為這是壞實踐，而且大多數家長不知道這件事，我們家長沒有選擇。
Good afternoon. My name is Rabia. I have been living in Hong Kong from 14 years. I have four kids. They are all born in Hong Kong.
外撥款嘅同埋學習嘅透明度同埋及問責性啦，咁將希望要求咧將誒呢一啲嘅撥款計劃同埋報告咧係擺上網。
More, we want to have equal Chinese learning opportunities. I want to, I want my kids to have same Chinese learning level. Chinese should be taught from the beginning.
我想提到，我 eldest 女兒的 Chinese 水準係好在小學，但係當她去到中學，佢哋就推佢後，把佢放喺一個較易嘅 Chinese 水準。
概念裏邊叫佢哋加一句啊，定係真係可以設立一格寫低對於非華語學生學校裏邊做咗咩措施咧？多謝主席。唔該，卓小姐。誒，We will now have Miss Phyllis John of Hong Kong Union，please。一誒，多謝主席。其實咧，我哋知道咧，政府咧係擺咗投放咗好多資源咧落去少數族裔誒嘅學語教嗰度㗎。噉。
咁自二零一四年開始咧，就已經增加撥款啦。咁每年咧，其實係誒提供多過二億元咧，係去支援非華語學生嘅教育學中文嘅教育學㗎。但係如果我哋睇翻咧教育局嘅文件咧，其實推出呢個學習架構啦，同埋有關嘅誒配套措施，甚至乎係個撥款咧。
確保誒實施呢個政策目標係必要㗎，但係咧，融樂會琴日咧係公佈咗一份報告咧，係關於誒呢一個學習架構同埋加外撥款嘅問責性啦。咁誒，我哋就發現咧，其實誒一般嘅誒公眾咧同埋誒家長咧係唔可以誒。
好難咧去監察呢個誒落實嘅過程同埋成效嘅。咁雖然教育局咧，佢喺撥款嘅計劃嗰度咧誒同埋報告咧撥款嘅報告咧，都有啲範本畀學校去填寫啦。而且咧，佢亦都係要求咧誒獲得誒呢個額外撥款嘅學校咧，要喺佢嘅學校週年報告上邊咧列出誒有關。
去誒支援非華語學生嘅誒中中文嘅誒措施啦，同埋一啲表現嘅。但係咧，教育局咧其實係冇一套嘅問責機制。噉我哋嘅研究咧就發覺，只有八成收呢啲額外撥款嘅學校咧係有將有關嘅資料咧係登上佢哋嘅網頁啦，或。
或者係等上佢哋嘅週年報告，而且咧係誒冇劃一嘅。有啲咧就會將佢哋嘅誒撥款嘅報告咧，成個報告等上網啦。有啲就冇，有啲就只係咧誒講咗佢嘅計劃或者佢嘅報告咧喺週年報告嗰度。噉我哋就似乎咧就冇一個即係比較統一啲嘅誒問責嘅機制嘅噉。
咁另外咧就係大部分嘅學校咧，雖然有講撥款點樣用啦，但係其實係冇提過誒呢個呢啲少數族裔嘅學生中文嘅進度或者表現同埋實施共用校園嘅措施啊。咁呢一兩樣咧，其實係家長係最關注嘅嘢咧，係冇咗嘅。噉我哋咧喺呢度咧，唔係話。
誒要針對學校啦，亦都唔係講緊要提供多啲嘅資訊畀誒家長去選校，而係咧希望有一個嘅誒問責嘅機制咧，能夠係確保呢個政策咧係實施得有完善嘅。咁所以我哋希望咧，教育局咧係可以增加誒呢個額。
When my kids were young, I didn't have enough school information to choose local school. I didn't know about schools' pod or extra tutorial class for my kids, so I ended up choosing English medium school. In those school, my kids didn't have enough chance to speak Chinese. I start I started to realise.
所以， in future， our
And there should be one level of learning Chinese. Every year should make progress and put them at a higher level.
所以，未來他們可以有平等的就業機會，並參與香港的進步。謝謝。
政府或者EDB會唔會話去誒檢討下睇下我佢哋可以做啲乜嘢去幫到我哋嘅非華裔小朋友？咁誒？
作為第二語言，The most school don't know how to teach Chinese to the children.
Is it not school website? Is all in the Chinese and parents have no choice, choose better for the children. I request to the government.
Different schools teach different levels Chinese. Is it not good? Chinese children and our children same levels. So of the Chinese, that's all my issue. Thank you so much.
佢係完全唔明白老師講緊乜嘢，咁唔代表佢係唔識誒計數咯。佢淨係咪數學，其他科都係，例如G.S.啊，係Level Studies啊，唔代表啲小朋友係冇能力去學咯。佢係識計數嘅，但係佢係唔明白老師係教佢乜嘢。所以我覺得誒呢個係好大嘅問題。仍然誒會唔會話誒？
在學校，如果我們孩子弱在中，文，他們給一個較易的中，文，級別。為什麼？如果我們孩子弱在英，文或數學，他們給額外的體育和輔導課。為什麼可以做在中，文？英，文或阿拉伯不是我們母語，但我們孩子可以記住它。
謝謝。可否現在請諾琳·阿斯卡？謝謝主席。我係諾琳。我係個家婦。我係巴基斯坦。我面臨中文學習的問題。當我到政府部門，EDB，學校溝通，所有表格用中文。
給 us a school information in English or Chinese, such as for the example application form website and open day leaflets in English. Parents will know about the school this way. Chinese language is the problem for me because is it not?
My mother language. I cannot teach my daughter Chinese homework for the study for Chinese example. We are not lazy. We went to the learn Chinese. I hope EDB will help us and EDB will give us the school the right way to the teach the Chinese.
Thank you, Miss Asker. We now have Miss Nagis Shakoor, please.多謝主席。誒，我叫Susan啦，噉我係香港出世嘅巴基斯坦人，喺香港讀書嘅，即係誒由幼稚園至到誒中學。咁咧，我就今日想講兩個問題，一個就係學中文。好多人覺得我哋誒非
bring them only to be able to bring the people to a level which can be achieved in just one year.
教育可以改善，但只有幾間提供中文教育課程。
一 child born to a lower class ethnic minority family is doomed to lead the same kind of quality of life generation after generation if they cannot communicate effectively within the Hong Kong local society.
especially要揾方法去整一個好嘅教材畀我哋咯。唔該，主席。唔該，主席哥。誒，We now have Mr. Said Ahmed, please. Ah, thank you, Chairman. Ah, क्या अलचाल हैं सबके, सब खारियत से हैं।
Seen around, I know people who have gained. I personally know people who have gained a A star in GCSE after learning it just for one year, and which again shows how low the bar is set for the alternative. And it's not fair to teach a language for 15 years throughout the local system only to be
So that is the kind of confusion many of the Hong Kong citizens feel when they apply for a job, when they try to communicate with a taxi driver, when they are trying to talk to a waiter. Many of the ethnic minority students who grow up in non-Chinese speaking households have little access to effective Chinese learning programmes, as many people have just mentioned.
話要小朋友係唔識中文，因為中文唔係我哋嘅母語。但係我覺得誒呢個唔係問題，因為而家今日呢個房咁多人，佢哋誒講英文好流利，可以溝通。但係佢哋個母語都唔係英文，所以我覺得如果有一個enough support誒，好細細個去學嘅話咧，噉我哋就一樣可以。
學到中文嘅好好嘅中文噉，我就誒有時諗點解學十二年嘅誒免費教育，但係到到依家我哋啲小朋友都學唔到一個語言咧？問題喺邊度？其實諗咗好耐之後，我發覺呢個唔係learning ability problem，呢個係一個systematic problem嚟嘅。咁如果我哋學唔到中文，噉我哋仍然學。
我哋個career development嗰度就誒一定追唔到學校咧，又有有好大嘅area係忽略咗嘅。例如誒學校會用中文去教其他科誒，我會畀個例子你啊誒。如果係數學嘅話，佢用中文去教佢啲題目，或者喺班入邊老師去教佢嘅話咧。
我哋啲小朋友唔係中文唔唔叻咯，噉樣佢會令到佢哋個誒result會再低啲。噉我想講咧，如果誒讀書讀得唔好，咁upward mobility更加我哋追唔到，更加難。第二個問題咧就係誒，我就想講好多學校就用普教中嘅，咁但係誒普教中咧對非華語小朋友係。
一個好大嘅困難，因為誒誒，我哋已經廣東話都唔得啦。咁點樣去用誒普通話去學Chinese咧？我就唔係話誒普通話唔重要嘅，但係我覺得香港咁多個個都係講誒誒廣東話，咁嗯，我哋應該要學好我哋嘅廣東話，冇話而家。
喺普教中嗰度就誒攞普通話去學中文咁噉樣，我哋就做唔到誒做唔到誒integration咯。噉我就誒想講誒十二年嘅免費教育，我哋點解學唔到中文一個一個一個language？誒普教中課誒話要小班化係好容易，一個係bonus嚟嘅課。
佢哋因為學校佢哋要學普通話，屋企可以學廣東話，但係課非話要上校咧。學校淨係學校一個地方，佢哋可以講到或者學到廣東話嘅咁誒。我就想誒問E.D.B點解好多嘢都係誒，即係個責任畀咗學校誒推咗畀佢話呢啲係school base嘅，但我。
覺得好多嘢都唔誒，即係家長冇得揀，因為呢啲全部都係責任畀畀曬學校老師去整一個教材出嚟去教佢哋。但係呢個負責呢個責任係應該EDB去做嘅。咁誒誒補多少少，我想講咧，香港咧嗰個population around八誒eight percent都係誒非華裔人啦。咁政府去整呢啲。
with two lessons a week.
我 believe it was due to the language barrier between us.
However, after my experience in learning Chinese at university.
other than that, I now do believe that the Chinese language taught in the mainstream schools in my time was not effective nor practical.
7,000 words and the topic in Chinese is對香港非華語學生學習廣東話調查與分析。
在 primary school，我 was not，我 was only taught English and Udu as a second language. Later in secondary school， the school suggested me to take French.
As I had no fundamental knowledge in Chinese, the school somehow had some basic Chinese classes until secondary three.
Speaking from my personal experience before four-year tertiary education, I had very little encounter with the local Chinese society, despite living in Hong Kong for over twenty years.
language gap, and allow minorities to be better integrated into the mainstream society. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Ahmed. We will now invite Mr. Masood Muhammad, please. Thank you, Chairman.
Self-created pinyin in order to remember the sound of a character. Hong Kong teachers do not adopt this approach, which could possibly be one of the reasons why ethnic minorities are unable to learn Cantonese effectively.
Throughout my learning experience, dictionary has been the handiest and the most helpful tool. According to what I've experienced, apps for learning Chinese on app stores are limited, and the apps available have various problems.
My name is Masood. I'm from Pakistan. I'm currently teaching English and Mandarin at a local mainstream secondary school in Taiwan. In 2014, I graduated from BNUZ Zhuhai with a bachelor's degree of arts in Chinese.
policy嗰陣時候有冇諗我哋咧？誒，政府會唔會覺得我哋係咪唔重要咧？噉我真係希望啦。General誒，generations after generation，政府直情係fail咗我哋，搞到我哋完全冇hope。我係香港出世嘅第二代，噉我到到依家都唔得。我啲家姐啲仔女第三代都係唔得，所以我覺得我好希望政府會e d b。
我 personally went through a relatively mainstream education system here in Hong Kong, starting from kindergarten, and I just finished my PhD last year at HKU. I consider myself amongst the lucky few of the ethnic minorities to have completed my education more or less smoothly through the local system. I was one of the first few ethnic minorities to enter the university.
Through the public exam system, and SCMP decided to publish my story as two among the winner circle. However, many of my peers from the school were not able to take up university courses because of their choice, because of Cantonese as a second language requirement, and even some English medium tertiary courses are taught in Cantonese.
So the current alternative we have for Chinese proficiency is at GCE levels, GCSE level, sorry. However, this is not enough to prepare them for tertiary education or even life, as again many people have just talked about. GCSE level Cantonese is not even the same complexity of fluency as local primary two, as from what people have told me or I've.
Further, that is all the current legislation deems appropriate that ethnic minority students in Hong Kong receive for now. The recent allocation of funds for improving the education of ethnic minorities has been majorly left to the discretion of the recipient schools. These institutions do not have much experience or guidelines as to how.
Many schools catering to the ethnic minorities call up NGOs to ask for suggestions on how to use the funding and for enhancing the Chinese second language programmes. The responsibility of educating these disadvantaged group of locals should not be left up to the institutional bodies. I believe, but to the Education Bureau itself, and with more transparency on the usage of the funds.
Chinese courses should be tailored and implemented by education bureaux starting at kindergarten. And with you guys' leadership, I'm sure improving Chinese education by introducing a locally tailored Chinese as second language program and providing additional support for learning to the younger generation will bring this.
我係能讀能寫超過兩千五百個字，並説流利的閩南語。在四年時間內，在最後一年的學士學位課程，我進行了一項研究，關於少數民族在學習中文時面臨的挑戰，並獲得積極回應。我今天帶了論文來這裡，它由兩部分組成。
和。
第一，係冇proper input method。
and for entering the job market，I think。
The education system over here systematically ignores.
That there are some people who are willing to pursue further education in Hong Kong.
Hi everyone. I would like to start by thanking everyone for making this hearing possible.
We now have Mr. Sehokter, please. Go there, Sehokter, please.
我係蘇浩達古德 Singh， born and raised in Hong Kong， and I'm presently teaching in Islamic College in Taiwan。
most of the dictionaries don't support this input method. They sometimes display wrong utting and according, and the audio recording for pronunciation of characters is often mispronounced.
I'm glad that I was given the opportunity to study at a local university, but however, I did face a lot of problems while I was pursuing academic journey in Hong Kong.
During my master's degree, I wasn't able to get into some courses just because the medium of instruction for those courses was Cantonese. So it really limited my choices during my postgraduate degree.
moving the rest of the levels to the university curriculum and Chinese proficiency test which is HSK can be taken into consideration and I think five or six levels should be the target of the students.
一job description might ask foreign applicants with a level five or better. And before I conclude this up, I have a few questions which I would like to ask the government. So my first question is that has the government considered? And we'll give you some more time afterwards, okay?
I wasn't able to apply for a PGD in secondary English. I was rejected from two universities just because their medium of instruction for some courses is Cantonese. It's creating a lot of hindrance for me to continue with my education in Hong Kong.
然後，教學方法在大學又turn out to be very effective. I managed to speed up my progress in a short period of time by pinion, which was developed in the fifties based on earlier form of romanisation. I believe pinion is a building block, as it is very important as a foundation. Learners.
feel comfortable with it. It is easy to remember and it is very helpful. When a beginner is engaged in a conversation with a local, there are high chances for the beginner to understand a lot of words. This is where the beginner can easily and quickly take notes by pinion and search for the words later on. What is more, my students often jot down.
And another issue which some people have mentioned today is regarding the CSL curriculum. Over the years, over over the years, numerous people have complained about IGCSE being too easy. In my opinion, we can divide this into six or seven levels, being four to five levels taught in secondary.
In addition to this, a lot of ethnic minorities in Hong Kong they face the same issue when they apply for university program. Their choices are limited because some of them are only taught in Cantonese. I will give one example which applies to me.
我 hope。
this kind of requirements could be taken into account.
我的父母、 brothers and sisters， and now my children's。
我睇自己係一個香港人，香港人睇㗎。
I acknowledge that Cantonese language is imperative in Hong Kong.
多謝主席。大家好，我叫漢·哈立德。
When I was young, I didn't have many opportunity to learn Cantonese.
Thanks for giving me a chance to express my feeling that how we live in Hong Kong life.
which can we which we can only overcome if the education system changes.
Everybody calls me KK. I'm born in Hong Kong. My family are the third generation living in Hong Kong.
但係，個系統 here 輸失認同，有啲香港人係獨一無二嘅。
因為香港是多文化社會，和such requirements creates obstacles for people like us.
校園的流利度要求是顯而易見的，然而校園對少數族裔學生的支持是質疑的。
If so, are they effective and to what extent? Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Soete. And we now have Mr. Khalid Khan, please.
and who might not be able to meet such requirements. Moreover, everyone in Hong Kong they have equal rights to education.
The school will also.
那將會所有益於未來香港。
to study and improve our writing and speaking.
那 means there are no chance for me to get those jobs.
It was because we don't have many choices to select the local schools.
那係唯一嘅選擇，畀我哋喺香港讀政府學校。
如果學校不願 willing to teach the students， who will do it?
在日，most of the time，children will spend their time in the schools in front of the teachers.
如果教師不 want to teach， who will teach them？ Parents can support them， only not to teach them。
All the work in Hong Kong, such as government jobs or high-level jobs, basic requirement is Cantonese, English, Mandarin now.
Use Cantonese language or Chinese language to teach the students. Your, the excuse will be your child is very difficult to catch up with the local students in the class.
在香港，所有 local 學校應接受任何 ethnic 少數學生到學，自 childhood 年齡。易學，不至到我年齡學，很難。
Except the private schools, we can learn English and French and no Cantonese or Chinese. French is not a good language for me as I live in Hong Kong or my future in Hong Kong.
我不能教我的孩子作業，因為我唔識寫中文，但係我知道我的孩子可以，而且會，因為佢哋自從幼稚園起喺本地學校開始學基本嘅知識。
我有非常少選擇來選我的小學和中學。一個是利辛州政府小學，和達利亞希普或塞爾斯卡杜裏中學。
Has the government done any evaluation on the Cantonese courses for adults, not just for teenagers who are studying in high school, as well as for ethnic minority students pursuing tertiary education?
Now my children is studying in local schools of Hong Kong. It was very difficult for me to find them local schools. When the teacher ask me, ask my children, do you know how to speak Cantonese? If you say no, they mostly reject them.
多謝，司長。
We are Hong Kongers.
我 want to say，香港係我哋嘅家。
如果你 all 治理 us 作為 Hong Konger， Hong Kong 可以 be 一個 colourful 城市。 at last， I want to say。
誒，跟住我哋議員發問時間咧，或者局長有冇需要一整體回應係必要嘅回應喺呢個階段，還是聽埋議員嘅查問查詢之後先一齊講都可以嚇。必你要選擇邊樣嘢？誒，或者我簡單回應下。好唔該你啊！我哋嘅誒，即係誒各位誒代表嘅發言。首先咧。
係好多謝大家誒出席今日誒呢一個誒嗰個同我哋去分享你哋嗰個經驗。咁誒，其實政府咧一直係非常之重視嚇，我哋係好重視非華語誒嘅同學或者係我哋嘅少數族裔喺香港社會咧係誒，即係同我哋係本地係一樣嘅，即係大家都係我哋。
都係香港人，誒，我香港係我哋嘅家，咁所以咧，教育局咧亦都係一直致力咧喺鼓勵同埋支援我哋嘅非華語同學咧，係盡早係融入啊，適應學校嘅生活，同埋係融入咧喺誒誒社會。咁所以喺誒頭先大家比較關心嘅幾個問題咧，第一咧就係由幼稚。
資源開始講起先啦。誒誒，最初嘅時候都有講到而家嗰個幼稚園嘅學習咧，我哋誒都係個政策上面咧，我哋係鼓勵咧係及早啊，亦都喺呢幾年咧，我哋見到咧係啊非華語或者係我哋少數族裔嘅小朋友入讀幼稚園嘅情況咧，係不斷咧係改善誒，越嚟越多嘅家長咧係會。
選擇將我哋嘅小朋友係送入去本地嘅幼稚園，畀佢哋能夠及早融入喺呢一個本地嘅語境，而同時為咗誒幫助我哋嘅誒即係誒少數族裔嘅小朋友能夠係適應學校嗰個學習啦。我哋喺各個方面咧都係做咗一啲嘅，即係喺政府嗰度咧係亦都係好努力去做包。
包括喺個指引嗰度咧，我哋係因應即係鼓勵學校係因應同學實際嘅情況，誒亦都為到誒有誒收呢啲非華語誒或者係少數族裔小朋友嘅幼稚園咧，係增加額外嘅資源去幫助我哋嘅老師咧，係能夠騰出空間去做專業發展喺老師嘅發展方面咧，我哋亦都。
都係即係誒，知道誒。當我哋呢一個融合教育喺幼稚園嗰度大力去推行嘅時候，我哋嘅師資配套係相當重要。所以由一八一九年起咧，我哋都要求每一間學校咧最少係有一名嘅教師咧係去完成嗰個認可嘅基礎訓練。咁頭先亦都有一啲嘅代表咧係提到咧啊。
同家即係家長誒同幼稚園嘅溝通嘅問題，咁或者係對於幼稚園收生嘅情況唔瞭解，咁呢個咧，我哋都係喺嗰個誒就住嗰個簡介誒誒個語言嘅翻譯啦，亦都包括咧係誒家長同學校嘅溝通有誒嗰個即時傳譯嘅服誒。
嗰個傳譯服務係可以申請噉，同時咧就係亦都係誒會誒為學校提供一啲嘅中英文版嘅一啲啊通報啊，或者一啲Q卡咧，係幫助學校同家長去溝通。咁呢個可能係喺誒，因為今年咧係落實第第一年落實嗰個免費嘅幼稚園教育。咁呢個咧。
畀老師做一個準成啊！真係一個一的出嚟嚇，請你真係考慮。
係幫老師嘅問題係你哋喺文件嗰度啊，即使你哋自己嘅文件都話三年級到四年級嘅引號課本。
About five days ago, I read in the South China Morning Post that there was a comment piece by two apparent education experts. They were calling for on this.
嗰個啊教材嘅編寫咧，啊，我覺得真係非常之好。啊，我唯一嘅誒有少少啊係投訴咧，就係網上我就想睇下你個教材究竟係啊，即係咩嘅內容咧，係冇得入。
係處於起步嘅階段，我哋都會知道咧一啲嘅措施咧係陸續需要優化。而對於嗰個誒頭先大大家提到咧係嗰個誒第二語言學習架構嗰個問責嗰個問題咧，我哋都係誒即係因為我哋都係投放好多嘅資源，我哋希望誒小朋友係學好中文，而點樣學好？
中文咧就係希望係通過係幫助佢哋小報紙，而能夠係誒喺呢一個誒有一個階梯性嘅呢個系統學習底下咧，係盡快融入主流嗰個課堂。咁嗰個所以嗰個架構嘅目標咧，係幫助我哋嘅非華語同學係融入誒主流嘅課堂，以致佢哋係唔會喺中。
文學習嗰度疏蝕嘅喺長遠嚟講，所以誒，我哋喺嗰個誒對學校嘅要求嗰度咧，剛才提到咧就話有啲係未必喺網上揾到誒學校嗰個即係發放佢哋誒點樣去誒誒推行呢一個即係或者係運用呢一個誒推行呢個第二語言學習架構。噉我我哋係。
想喺呢度咧，同大家去講咧，其實學校係好多種嘅模式，係去啊，即係話讓家長知道佢哋點樣去支援誒啲誒小朋友喺學校嗰個學習嘅點樣運用嗰啲資源誒，包括咧其實佢哋係誒需要咧係誒有一個長進嘅計劃啦、報告啦，係要喺校董會嗰度通。
而每年咧亦都係需要向教育局係去匯報，咁同時咧就係我哋亦都係會誒，即係有個誒，即係佢哋所自己自評嘅結果咧，我哋亦都會有誒外評啊等等係去做核實嘅。咁此外咧，家長點樣得知咧？除咗喺網上之外咧，其實學校會通過家長日啦，或者。
係學校個刊物啊，等等多元嘅形式咧，係同家長去分享介紹。咁所以大家咧，其實就唔使話，因為誒有啲學校亦都會選擇放喺網上嘅形式，但係就唔係只係單一嘅噉。所以各位家長其實如果關心嘅話咧，係可以咧誒通過呢啲各種嘅渠道去了解咁誒。
另外第三方面咧，就關於嗰個誒，即係學生資助咧。頭先都有啲同學提到咧，就唔係太過知道誒攞到個資訊。噉我哋而家咧都係就即係亦都係誒好努力咧。第一咧就係話喺嗰個簡誒誒嗰個誒資料簡介嗰度咧，我哋會有誒各種嘅少數誒族裔嘅。
語言翻譯嘅版本啦，另外亦都會喺誒網頁嗰度咧係專業嘅網頁咧嗰度係去揾得到。咁誒，同時咧就係話嗰個頭先提到咧，就係除咗中英文版嘅誒申請表之外，咧亦都會有一個嘅誒傳譯同埋填表嘅服務，如果有需要嘅話，咁仲同埋咧，我哋都會鼓勵學
校啦，或者係我哋教育局咧，會都會同誒，即係去誒同學校啊，或者係分區去誒舉辦一啲嘅簡介會，幫助家長去了解呢啲申請嘅程序。噉我或者大概簡單回應。好，唔該，局長。誒，跟住嚟到委員發言時間。我哋今日都有個動議咧，需要處理嘅。咁而家或者我哋預會喺會喺四分鐘先啊，揾。
少少誒，首先請莫萬正議員。誒唔該，主席。就首先咧，我認為教育局咧喺誒我哋少數族裔小朋友學習中文嘅方面咧係有做到嘢嘅，尤其是你最新呢一個喺三年小學三年級到四年級銜接嗰度。
Thank you.
our kids, Chinese in Mandarin rather, so.
你 know very impressive. I do suspect some schools are teaching.
Public money a year to help with our children to learn Chinese, and yet the effect doesn't seem to be.
We need to blend in. We are Hong Kongers, right? So the fact that we we spend more than, well, some 200 million dollars.
At the end of the day, they can't associate Chinese once they step out of the school. So I wish the EDB would do something. They would check on the schools to make sure that our children are learning proper Cantonese.
你要登入，但係你登入又要填表，又要咩咁嚇係廣大佢哋嗰個教學中心嗰度噉，我就唔係幾滿意。我就唔知可唔可以你哋事後畀啲誒，即係誒嚇畀啲三浦我睇睇嚇。呢個真係唔該曬先噉，但係啊，好坦白講，呢啲係教材。
唔係真正嘅課本嚟嘅咯，係教材嚟嘅咯。我再同意就係阿卓文寶小姐講嘅，你哋就一路擔心話我哋小朋友咧誒，佢哋嘅中文嘅水準參差，所以咧就好難有正規嘅第二語言課程。但係唔係㗎，我哋小朋友學英文一樣好差。
今次啦，三四年班有啲甩甩聲，有啲就連啊誒Good morning都唔肯講，咁冇解㗎嘛。但係你一定教育局咧，希望你有一個啊，即係一條線喺度。你所有嘅學習第二語言咧，一定係有一條線嘅。有人好啲，有人差啲啊。
唔得啊！My second point is, I'm so glad about the integration business you were mentioning, and about living in a linguistic environment. Right? I have to say, I perfectly agree with Miss Shakur. Right?
Well, their advocacy is that ethnic minority children in Hong Kong should be learning Chinese in Mandarin, and that gave me a fantastic fright. Now, even our education deputy chief is talking about integration.
兩個都係意見，有冇咩特別嘅簡單或者我要回應咧？好啊，誒多謝誒主席，多謝議員個提問。咁頭先提到咧教材嗰度咧，其實咧就係誒噉，即係有一套咧就係有課本啦，有作業啦嚇。噉我哋都稍後可以即係畀啊議員睇一睇啦，教師用書啦。咁呢個係誒即係而家係出。
咗誒，即係第一冊嘅噉。另外誒，第二語言課程嗰度咧，誒頭先提到咧，其實誒我哋唔希望咧係做一個本地嘅，即係叫做中文作為第二語言嘅課程。其實係有一個國面向國際，因為如果我哋噉樣做嘅話咧，亦都係會浪費咗我哋小朋友嗰個時間，反而咧係。
啊！我哋而家做嘅係用作誒第二從第二語言學習者嘅角度咧，係誒嗰個教學方法嘅調適嗰度個角度入手咧。因為長遠嚟講，我哋剛才講我哋嘅目標係希望我哋小朋友係融入我哋主流嘅課程，以致佢哋唔會學淺咗，亦都唔係學一套唔係我哋本。
本地嘅中文課程，咁所以呢個咧就係話點解我哋會係用第二語言嘅學習架構，係去幫助我哋小朋友係以小步子進化融入本地嘅課程。第三咧就係嗰個教學語言嘅，剛才阿毛議員提到教學語言嘅問題咧，其實究竟係用普教中啊、粵教中啊呢啲咧，我哋一路教育局都。
佢都即係香港，都係佢哋嘅家。
都係有一啲其他方面畀學生嘅選擇嘅。
噉，但係我哋亦都知道咧，誒。
大學會唔會有啲中階一啲又比GCE較高嘅課程協助到佢哋？唔該，主席。聽到意見聽到㗎啦嚇。誒，跟住請張超雄議員計。
係，主席啊！我哋好高興聽到副局長話，政府好重視非華語嘅同學佢哋嘅學習機會，同埋佢都話即係。
非華語或者少數族裔嗰個貧窮嘅情況咧，係比一般香港嘅人咧係嚴重一啲嘅。噉我哋亦都知道教育同。
你回翻畀我咧，就係嗰個係即係職業語境嗰個啊嘛，我就係話可唔可以喺正規嘅即係高階一啲嘅中文嘅課程，可以喺大學嘅階段入邊持續提供到畀佢哋。高長。
貧窮係有直接關係。如果少數族裔係喺教育度可以學有所成，佢哋脱離貧窮嘅機會咧，會大大增加。噉我相信呢個都係政府嗰個誒信念嚟嘅。噉我想問誒，即係到咗今天。
係強調係要考慮學生嘅能力啦、佢哋嘅需要啦、學校嘅語境啦，同埋老師嗰個嘅能力等等各方面嘅因素條件嘅，就唔係話誒即係一刀切或者係誒讓學生係冇得揀。咁呢個我哋教育局係有好清晰嘅指引嘅。問，但係我問題係最緊要唔好。
好佢係被逼，佢哋係想學中文咧，但係學中文嘅時候，原來要講普通話，真係大鑊。真係噉，佢完全出咗課堂都唔知發生咩事，係嘛時間關係咧，我哋必須要繼續。誒，我哋啱啱亦都收到啊，郭榮亨議員一個動議，我都認為係同我哋嘅主題有關嘅，噉我都因轉頭會處理嘅。誒，我哋。
而家仲有四位同事要發問我哋，或者可能輕輕揸翻緊少少啦。跟住我哋，或者都讀個名：，韋韋兆堅議員、張超雄議員、郭榮興議員同潘少平議員嘅。啊，請啊韋兆堅議員答四分鐘。多謝主席，冇事，我就行開咗。唔知有冇嘈翻阿梅議員講啊？誒，目前嗰個誒大學咧，其實誒缺乏一啲適合少少族裔學生提升中文。
能力嘅課程嘅，我相信各方都知道。噉我就誒，當然咧，我哋見到其實係有啲改善嘅，即係包括小族裔個大學嘅入學率，其實都係稍為有啲增長啊。不過結果就係咧，佢縱使入大學個率誒改善咗都好，到最終佢順利畢業之後，佢嗰個。
個中中文嘅水平嘅程度，似乎都係未跟得上，包括出嚟要投考唔同嘅部門或者政府部門嘅工作嘅一個限制。噉我就諗，即係有具體政策建議，可唔可以誒考慮喺大專或者大學設立一啲比誒G C S E或者G C E程度高一啲嘅中文課程，畀佢持續咁去學到。
噉就從而涵接到個日後喺大學畢業，佢有其實有可能有相關嘅專業水平，有誒英語能力都好好卓越。但係唯獨是呢樣嘢，讓佢喺本地嗰個生活同埋發展長期個即係政府成日講人生規劃啊，即係冇咗規劃呢度，噉就斷咗呢咁啲升link，導致佢有好大嘅影響。我希望。
可唔可以具體回應下有會唔會考慮讓啲持續進修中文嘅機會，讓啲小數族裔喺大學嘅時候可以繼續？唔該，主席。好啊，局長。好啊，啊多謝議員，多謝主席。剛才咧提到咧就係啊兩個方面嘅一個咧就係話學生入大學嗰個即係中文嘅學習咧，其實我哋通過啊考試啊嗰個即係可以選擇。
誒前誒GCE或者IGCSE嗰個資歷係去幫助佢哋可以誒，即係唔會畀因為語文咧係阻礙咗佢哋入學。另外咧，而家亦都多咗一個咧，就係應用中文學習。咁呢個咧亦都係免費提供，即係全免費提供畀所有誒，即係中四至中六嘅學生。咁而至於剛才提第二方面提到咧，就關於咧。
大學之後咧，嗰個中文學習咧，其實我哋而家係係有一個職業中文課程咧，係畀誒我哋嘅誒少數族裔嘅朋友咧，係繼續去學習佢嘅中文嘅，係以至去適應佢就業嘅需要。主席，佢都誒，我唔知副長咪我表達得唔清楚，冇答緊個問題咯，就係話我知嘅嗰啲係我哋知道有，跟住你。
誒其實咧就誒語言嘅比G A G C更高嘅水平嘅誒其實喺誒而家香港嗰個誒課程裏邊咧，我我相信咧即係大學會因應佢嗰個需要噉，但係一般咧中文而家中文係嘅課程咧，或者係其他語言嘅課程咧，就誒相信就誒未必係學位嘅課程，但係。
你畀佢選修咪得咯嚇？你畀佢選修啫嘛。佢有權選修咪得咯。我哋畀個機會，我就而家佢連機會都冇㗎嘛。重點係即係我哋聽到咗投訴就係我都想中文好啲啊！我我尋日好好努力入埋大學，點知出到嚟我嗰我縱使我唔知你有冇睇報紙啊？上一兩年都年年都報嘅攞埋法律學位。
誒攞埋其他專業學位，但係出到嚟嗰個嘅發展機會，甚至考政府公就因為中文未達到標，噉我覺得呢個係好好荒謬嘅。主席係咪好唔合理？噉你畀個選擇佢啫，即係你有呢個課程睇過。我當然知道唔係個個都會學嘅，但係我哋而家係冇呢個選擇，我就覺得令人哋舊病係咁咯。係。
睇下嗰個數字咧，或者誒。
嗰個我頭先講一啲問題，可以嘛，副長？交翻佢下，唔該曬。跟住我哋請啊，郭榮亨議員，唔該。
噉，我覺得呢啲就係去睇翻嗰個結果啊嘛。咁如果你哋有好重視嘅話，有冇就住呢個情況做過任何嘅分析？
喺幼兒教育嗰度，即係頭先團體講，誒佢哋小朋友學習語言最好嘅時間黃黃金期啦，就喺嗰個階段。
三以上個絕學嘅情況，誒，比一般香港學生有冇分別咧？然後入到大學，其實佢哋入大學個比例，相對於一般香港學生，即係華語同非華語個比較，又係點樣咧？
誒同埋有啲乜嘢，即係如果見到個問題嘅話，誒有啲乜嘢嘅功夫會做咗？你誒即係我知你數白籃可以數好多啦。咁但係即係不如你講講，即係你對嗰個問題有冇一個掌握先咧？我話局長。
局長有冇嘢補充？我我哋會向大學反映啦。咁但係一般嚟講，大學嗰啲課程咧，其實佢係不分種族啊、種族或者不分誒誒誒咩背景，主要就係符合佢嗰個即係學科課程嘅基本要求，佢就會收嘅。咁所以咧，最緊要就係有冇一啲合適嘅課程畀我哋啊，即係少數族裔嘅。
朋友嗰個程度嘅中文咁呢個，我哋會誒即係誒向大學嗰方面去反映嗰個需要。主席，我補多一句，一而家就係冇啊，即係一步登天，同香港買樓一樣啊！主席，即係一係一係就攬到頂，你噉啊，中間有冇啲平少少嘅？同樣道理，即係誒少少族又有特定嘅需要嘅。我希望即係希望你嗰個承諾係做到咧。
咁喺呢個階段裏邊，而家其實有幾多少數族裔或者非華語嘅學生係喺一個即係所謂誒廣東話語境嘅環境入邊咧？幾多係喺一啲主要係收取非華語學生嘅幼稚園或者幼兒。
學校裏邊，即係因此，佢哋個預警咧未必係可以係一個即係廣東話預警。咁去到誒小學、中學，我哋知道，你哋亦都有啲即係支援啦。噉佢哋其實嗰個絕學嘅情況，即係少數族裔去到誒中。
係好啊！誒，剛才提到咧，就住誒嗰個誒非華誒，即係少數族裔嘅小朋友喺誒本地學校嗰個讀入讀嘅情況咧，我哋而目前咧中小學其實加埋咧有萬九位嘅小朋友就喺我哋本地嘅誒資助或者直資嘅學校裏邊咧係讀書嘅。
咁誒，當中係九千幾位，九千六咧係小學啦，九千四咧係中學。咁而幼稚園方面咧，喺啊，即係我哋嘅啊啊嗰個免費幼教嘅誒計劃底下嘅咧，有五千幾位，五千三百位，即係喺本地嘅幼稚園，而加埋曬其他，包括喺國際學校或者係喺其他嗰啲。
啊！
個嘅階段性。
嘅目標啊，同班友係脱歐嘅個目標係唔係確立得好？第二方面咧，就係話究竟係一個學語教策略。
Could be used in in a good way, in a constructive way that would actually help the people who are here expressing their concerns about the future of their children. Thank you.
嘅幼稚園裏邊嘅咧，就有一萬二千幾嘅啊小朋友非華語個學生。噉我哋見到咧，其實喺誒一七一八年咧，我哋嘅非華語學童咧係啊分佈喺三百九十幾間嘅中小三百九十間嘅中小學裏邊。我哋睇到嗰個其實而家咧普遍咧融入本地。
嘅情況咧，係一路一路咧係改善當中嘅。咁呢個咧就係就住誒非華語同學咧喺本地就學嘅情況。咁而至於佢哋入大學嗰個情況咧，佢哋大概咧誒即係考入去大學嗰個咧就誒千幾位裏邊有二百幾位咧係通過咧聯招係誒誒誒入咗去大學嘅。
誒一千一百八十六位，咁其中咧有二百七十七位咧，即係今年以舊年嚟計啦。咁嗰個比例咧，即係嗰個入大學，即係通過誒呢一個噉樣嘅誒聯招嘅方法入大學嘅誒，我哋會睇到其實個誒同本地應該係相差唔係好遠嘅。個主席，不如請佢會後誒將嗰。
Thank you, Chairman, and thank you, members of the community, to come and express your views. And we wholly agree with you when you say that you are part of Hong Kong, you are a Hongkonger, just as all of us sitting here, and that your children deserve the same education.
rights as our children, as everyone's children. So I think that much is clear. I don't think anyone here would disagree with you, with that. But it is a matter of implementing that right. It is a matter of honouring that obligation that we all have towards our children to ensure they have the best.
Education possible that would equip them to work and to be successful and to realise their full potential in Hong Kong and in any society, really, that should be worthy of the name of a first-class city like Hong Kong. So what we are seeing here is that the government has spent.
800 million dollars now for the fourth year in implementing this learning framework. But what we're hearing the feedback is that a lot of parents can't even access the information on the school websites or on other through other means as to what the schools are.
實際做用那筆錢，一收到，什麼種教育材料，他們提供給非中文説的學生學中文，什麼種老師，他們提供，什麼種資源，他們提供，來讓這些非中文説的學生學中文，所以我覺得這些資訊。
That you need to extract from the schools and get the schools to be more transparent about what they are actually doing to help these non-speaking, non-Chinese-speaking students. So transparency is very important, as UNISON has pointed out in their report. And also, I would like to know when you say you are doing.
做一個review，起頭，of the whole learning framework，where you are at exactly with that review，and what steps are you going to take in after you complete the review? How are you going to improve the framework so that the taxpayers' money, 800 million dollars,
誒局長有冇回應？好啊，或者咧誒誒，各議員誒嘅兩個問題，第一個問題就係關於咧，我哋即係嗰個嘅誒誒第二語言嘅架構咧，點樣係讓家長咧係知道多一啲嗰個問責係點樣？誒，我陣間咧或者請阿誒同事咧係可以誒誒講一講咧，就係我哋。
誒一路咧，每一年都有收集咧學校嗰個誒實施嘅情況，而點樣讓家長去知道咧？我哋係剛才提到咧，係通過各種嘅模式，除咗話喺網上係掛個報告出嚟之外咧，其實更加重要嘅係喺家長日啦、面對面啦，或者係通過學校一啲嘅實際嘅誒活動咧，畀家長咧係去了。
解更重要就比起咧，就咁畫一一個表格係誒，我相信咧家長可以瞭解嘅係更多。咁而且咧，我哋一路都係鼓勵咧嗰個學校同家長之間嘅溝通同埋合作嘅。咁所以係冇需要咧係話誒唔畀即係唔讓家長知道。第二方面咧就係就住嗰個架構嗰個檢討咧咁誒，我聽。
係局長。
誒，跟住請麥美娟議員。
去咁原來咧，佢哋講咧就係。
業界同前線唔同持份者溝通，再去誒檢視嗯。
作一個比例上嘅一個安排，噉我想了解下政府會唔會喺呢方面會即係會調整呢個噉啊資助嘅安排咧？唔該。
睇下咧，同事會唔會有補充啦？我哋其實而誒冇即係誒喺三每三年咧係會做誒呢一個嘅檢討誒睇視乎咧嗰個學即係深淺嘅程度啦。學校實施嘅時候誒誒即係誒學生個表現係點樣，就去檢視嗰個框架嘅情況嘅。咁或者我請睇下同事有冇補充邊位教務同事？
先生係我首先係就嗰個嘅學習架構嗰個檢討嘅着眼點誒，有兩個角度去睇。一咧就係嗰個架構本身嗰個設計嗰個深淺係咪適中？我哋嗰個所謂階段性嘅目標確立得係咪正確？咁喺呢個階段性目標嗰度咧，我想澄清一點咧，就係。
係我哋同第一語言學習唔同咧，就係大家起步點一樣嘅時候咧。無論喺小三啊、小六啊或者中三嘅階段咧，因為大家起步一樣咧，所以我哋會估計佢嗰個進展係差不多。但係喺第二語言學習嗰度咧，我哋解釋過咧，因為大家起步點有啲人喺小三，但係佢第一年學。
有啲喺小一，佢係第一年學噉，所以嗰個階段性嘅目標咧，係應該以佢學習中文嘅歷程有幾長就一個目標，唔係同佢嗰個班級就一個目標。咁所以我哋檢視呢一個嘅學習架構嘅時候，我就會留意翻嗰個。
嘅問題導致到佢達唔到嗰個目標所求咁呢個咧係我哋日常去做探訪、去觀課、去睇學生嗰個課業嘅時候咧，得到一啲好具體嘅印象咧，回歸翻呢一個學習架構應該係點樣去完善化啊？多謝主席。唔該，李生。誒，跟住嚟請潘少平議員。
唔該，多謝主席。咁亦都多謝啲團體代表嚟畀意見啊。咁事實上，即係大家都會知咧，即係誒學習呢個語言咧，係應該越細個越早嘅學習咧係越好。咁正話佢哋都反映咗咧，就係即係事實上，即係要。
小説在嘅朋友咧，響掌握我哋呢啲誒華語或者廣東語咧，係應該有一個語言環境同埋越早學習。咁當然咧，亦都正話有團體或者有誒朋友反映咧，就誒而家即係響教育局咧，其實都有關於嗰個誒幼稚園嘅收八。
明就有資助嗰個安排啦。噉就誒，佢哋亦都提到有啲團體咧做反映咧，就係即係有啲收一至七個嘅幼稚園咧，都有成三百幾間嘅誒幼稚園。咁誒，我唔知道政府點樣去處理呢個問題，因為佢哋覺得咧係需要喺呢方面咧個資助額咧。
係好啊，多謝主席。咁誒頭先提到咧，就係我哋誒就住幼稚園嗰個誒資助嘅方式啦。噉我哋而家係八位以上咧，就會有一位大概誒有一個誒幼稚園老師嘅新津嘅一個津貼。咁而一至七位咧，我哋係希望佢哋係通過融入啊沉浸嘅方式。咁所以我哋係會。
誒唔係用派，即係唔係用津貼嘅形式，而係用誒對教師嗰個校本支援嘅形式嘅。咁至於嗰個支援嘅模式係點樣誒能夠最有效咧？可能誒經過即係實施之後咧，誒將來會同業界溝通啦。噉我哋再檢討一下嗰個誒支援係可以點樣係誒做好啲。有冇跟進？
問題啊，好似即係嗱，我我睇翻咧就社聯咧有個建議咧，即係用即係一至四名嘅，即係個收生咧四分一啊，個個老師資助，即係呢一種噉嘅，會唔會係相對好過你話為七名以內又用嗰個噉樣安排噉啊？會唔會嗰個資助上咧會？
其他方法嘅。
表格嘅格式啊，各方面嗰啲咧，我哋可以即係翻去咧，我哋反映翻誒研即係研究下嗰個跟進嘅辦法。嗯。
咁咧每年咧，即係包括每年收到幾多個非華語嘅報名錶，當中咧有幾多學生有面試機會，而最後有幾多有幾多咧係成功入讀？
更加公平啲咧，呢個即係教育局會唔會真係會進一步考慮其他嘅建議，再作一個決定咧？局長，好，誒收到議員嘅意見嘅，正如我剛才講咧，其實就誒我哋係因應住啊嗰個唔同嘅目標啦，提供唔同嘅支援。咁而即係至於會唔會改變嗰個方式咧？我哋係會同。
主席，我想跟進翻頭先潘少平議員嗰個問題，都係幼稚園嗰個問題，因為誒，大家我哋一路講緊嗰啲誒學習架構嗰啲，都係講緊喺誒中小學啊噉。但係其實喺幼稚園咧，其實係小朋友嗯第一次離開屋企接觸呢個社會嘅機會嚟㗎嘛，噉佢哋。
都係喺即係，如果我哋讀language嘅就會知道嗰段時間其實係佢哋最好去學習語嘅時候嚟嘅。咁但係誒點樣可以令到佢哋有一個好嘅幼稚園嘅誒學習生活咧？咁誒，我哋頭先同潘少明員都講咗，好多幼稚園都係要八個以上先至可以攞到嗰筆嘅資助啦。
啦，如果八個以下噉就逐個嚟攞啦。咁但係對於有啲即係校長都同我哋講，佢哋一個困難就係第一步就係招生嗰度，即係佢係要是有學生收咗入嚟，先至有額外嘅資源。咁有時啲學生點樣去誒？佢喺招生嘅時候點樣去令到啲誒誒？
誒少數族裔嘅家長知道幾時係收生，點樣填入學表，點樣做呢啲噉嘅工作咧？咁咁其實都有啲支援畀佢哋。咁到到好啦，有一個學生入咗嚟，佢啦收夠第第六、第七個嘅時候，佢哋又唔知點算啦嚇。噉啊，到到收到第八個好開心嘅時候咧，一路收落。
誒，佢哋嗰啲學誒每個學期嘅學習咧，我諗副顧長知啦。佢哋要寫翻一個報告學習嘅報告，關於每一個小朋友畀翻家長嘅咁嗰份報告咧，老師啊，梗係用中文寫㗎啦。咁極其量就意文都係揾人寫英文啦。咁但係其實揾唔到人咧，可以再譯到一啲語言係畀翻佢哋嘅家長睇。
咁所以其實呢啲噉嘅支援係咪即係其實直誒教局可以統一去協助，無論中小學或者係幼稚園喺收生呢啲，即係佢哋喺當佢哋都未收到學生嘅時候，就應該畀啲噉嘅支援佢哋。而且呢啲係令到我哋啲家長咧係更加容易咧可以知道嗰個教育嘅。
制度係點？究竟點樣畀幾時畀小朋友係入學讀幼稚園係點啊？噉，所以我覺得希望即係政府能夠統一噉樣去畀誒有關嘅幼稚園、中小學，佢哋一啲可能呢啲誒統一嘅格式啊、入學嘅表格啊等等，等佢哋去誒容易啲畀家長去誒溝通。另外就係其實我又覺得誒。
誒透過咧嗱，幼稚園其實係比較好嘅，因為中小學可能就功課，佢哋已經去到要去學功課量已經多㗎啦，學習已經有壓力㗎啦。幼稚園嘅時候係咪可以透過幼稚園去做一啲家長嘅誒workshop嗰啲叫誒工作坊咧？咁咪令到其實因為我哋都知道好多誒小數。
做嘅家長誒特別可能係媽媽，佢哋自己對於嗰個中文嘅掌握都唔係好好嘅。咁或者佢哋都唔好瞭解嗰個社會嘅，係咪可以透過做呢啲工作坊，既可以令到佢哋瞭解學校係點樣，即係個成個教育制度係點，佢哋嘅小朋友係讀書係點，又可以做啲parent education，令到誒透過。
噉樣令到家長亦都可以融入嗰個社會，同我哋一齊。咁所以，我覺得係咪即係誒可以喺即係畀多啲資源啦，特別喺幼稚園嗰度，我哋善用我哋誒幼稚園嗰啲誒同學，佢哋啱啱入學嘅時候嗰個機會，等佢哋誒無論係畀佢哋一個好嘅環境去學習個語言啦，亦都畀佢哋誒有一。
個機會令到同家長咧都可以人透過噉樣而係同我哋嘅社會啊，多啲去了解我哋社會嘅事啊，或者我哋教育制度啊噉。咁簡單，會議局長。好啊，多謝議員嘅意見。噉就住即係話誒，我哋點樣可以支援誒多啲幼稚園嘅家長咧，係讓佢哋可以幫到小朋友嗰個學習。咁包括咧，可能喺嗰啲誒。
誒，布美娟有冇緊時間？但係局長，嗰個嗰個資源嗰個畀嘅津貼嗰度又會點咧？即係嗱，而家嗱誒一至七就咁多，八至無限又係咁多。咁其實你會唔會考慮喺嗰個津貼嗰度再畀多啲支援畀啲幼稚園咧？嗰樣簡單。正如頭先誒，即係我都誒簡單回應過咧，就係話。
please.
And my second question is that.
If any research has been done in this regard?
Yeah, actually, my first question was like, has the government considered introducing Cantonese youth ping system to teach the EM students?
叫滿足度。Although I promised Mr. Mohammed another opportunity for you to make a suggestion to government, would you like to do that in a couple of minutes' time?
所以，我哋亦都我我思誒，我哋亦都係唔會要求學校噉樣去將啲學生分類去決定收唔收，或者係睇下佢點解收唔收噉樣嘅。係。
And my third question is that, what are the considerations of the government of not introducing this youth ping system for Cantonese learning, for students whose mother tongue is not Cantonese?
就住誒，即係幼稚園誒，佢哋收誒非華語同學或者係誒誒少數族裔同學嗰個情收生嘅情況咧，我哋有冇收集數據啊？或者具體點樣做？同埋咧，嗰個誒家長嘅資訊，或者請我同事咧係補充一下。
其實呢一個支援模式咧，我哋誒除咗話睇錢之外咧，我哋都睇學校嗰個實際需要嘅。咁所以就話點樣先係最實際幫到學校咧？我哋真係需要同學校誒同前線去傾完咧。噉我哋唔排除係其實可以誒，即係話喺個誒津貼啊或者其他方面去誒，即係研究下嗰啲可行嘅。
好，小家樽完唔該。好唔該，主席，即係正如正話咧，公聽會即係好多朋友所講咧，其實我哋議員辦事處咧，成日都收到好多小族嘅家長咧，去打電話嚟投訴咧，就話因為睇唔到中文咧，所以咧就好難誒得到一啲報名嘅資訊，以至於就報唔到名啊，咁幼稚園搞到咧就讀唔。
到幼稚園啊，噉樣就算而家有曬嗰啲所謂嘅收生指引都好咧，問題仍然存在。所以我問題咧係有三部分。第一部分咧就係咧，即係有關嗰個學生，嗰有關嗰個學校概覽咧，文件寫明咧係有學生支援呢一項，會用劃一形式喺學校嘅概覽中表示嘅。噉我想問問質。
仔細啲啊！唔好介意咩叫畫一形式咧，係一句啊，定係一定係一行啦，定係一個表噉樣去表列曬所有支援措施畀嗰啲E.M.嘅家長去參考咧。第二個問題就係點樣加強嗰個收生嘅監察，即係政府咧就會唔會考慮咧收集喺幼稚園嘅收生嗰個數據？
第三部分問題就係政府會唔會抽查幼稚園嘅網頁睇誒睇睇下嗰啲睇唔到睇唔明中文嘅家長係咪真係能夠揾到有關報名嘅資訊咧？噉樣啊，問得好具體。請主席咪誒幫我繼續跟進一下。長唔計好啊！多謝主席。剛才提到咧嗰個概覽誒。
用劃一嗰個形式係咩意思咧？噉我哋其實而家咧就同誒家校合作事宜委員會，因為嗰個概攬係家校合作事宜委員會誒幫誒家長係去出嘅，咁所以我哋係同佢哋討論當中嘅，即係點樣嘅資訊先係對家長最有幫助。咁所以呢個咧，我哋係誒誒同時係跟進緊嘅。而至於咧啊～
誒，你睇唔該，係多謝誒主席，多謝議員嘅分享。咁咧原則上，我哋咧而家嗰個收生安排咧，就正如議員所講咧，我哋有一個嘅收生安排嘅指引嘅內邊咧，其實都好清楚咧，就要要求我哋嘅有住院咧參加計劃嘅有住院咧，其實係上載佢哋所有嘅收生嘅程序啦。
佢哋嗰個嘅誒criteria，佢哋嘅準則啦，等等都要係中英文版本嘅。況且，如果我哋係亦都會係加誒，即係畀咗一啲嘅template嗰啲啊，幼兒園啦，以致到佢有啲嘅範本去跟隨啦。咁所以咧，喺我哋每年咧誒十一月開始招生之前嘅十月咧，其實我哋都會有。
一啲嘅誒，即係調查，即係我哋嘅分區嘅同事啊，我哋嘅同事都會同學校每一間咧都去睇翻佢哋嘅網頁啦，或者係同佢哋日常嘅接觸內邊啊，去問下佢哋咧，或者係去了解佢哋，清晰翻佢哋完全係跟翻我哋嘅指引去做嘅。所以咧喺誒呢幾年咧，我哋推行咗呢一個。
話收生安排之後咧，其實各樣嗰個情況咧亦都有一啲嘅長足嘅進步係。誒主席，我想跟進啦嚇。第一點咧就係誒，我哋希望係表列形式啊誒去講，去比較容易清楚明白。第二點咧就係，最近講嗰個數嗰個數據咧係講緊咧非華語嘅報名錶收到幾多份，有幾多學生可以被interview。
有幾多學生最後收咗呢？一個數字有冇？如果有嘅話，就請你哋麻煩你可唔可以提交過往嗰兩年咧有關嘅數字？麻煩主席啊，局長有冇或者係啦？嗰個會後睇一睇，因為我我我嘅理解咧就係誒，即係我哋誒學校收生咧，就應該不論種族、不論文化背景嘅噉。
Okay.
好啊，唔該你。
誒黃靜怡，你想自己讀出嚟啊？定還是由畀書幫你讀咧？
誒知道嗰個動議嘅內容咧，就我哋都讀一讀，可能會好啲。
誒，畀處理，我你讀，你還是得，我幫你讀。
有意見，冇意見嘅話，我哋可以咁做法嚇。好，另一個第二個動議嘅話，請郭榮興議員你動議。
好誒，由於我哋時間關係咧，我哋去將要第二節嘅。不過方便大家，為方便書書安排咧，我哋或者休會三分鐘嘅時間，我哋馬上第二節開始好嘛？唔該曬大家。
指引詳述本地少數族裔學生在各級應達至怎樣的中文水平。多謝主席。好，亦都同樣我哋冇乜特別大嘅問題嘅話，我哋亦都可以當通過咗就處理咗佢啦。
中文咧，其實未必係對誒小朋友咧去學中文係最有幫助，因為佢個負擔係會重咗，佢反而要即係佢要學多學多一套，而長遠嚟講咧，因為中文係一個象形誒嘅文字嚟㗎，咁如果用語音標示去學習咧，呢個對於誒幼年嘅小朋友咧，其實未必最有效嘅。
我留意都係對唔住誒，唔係我就覺得誒，我麻煩你，麻煩副局長可以check清楚啦，即係唔可以係啊，唔好淨係思疑啦。如果冇嘅話，希望希望有翻呢個數字啦。唔該，跟進啦，下個局長，唔該你。我哋見到周浩軒原有舉手示意，不過因為我哋而家其實已經去第二節時間或者第二轉嘅時候，如果你唔介意嗰陣時問咧，亦都係同事想要第二轉嘅，都恐怕問。
Right, any brief response to the questions?誒，關於咧用粵拼學廣東話咧，其實而家咧我哋即係如果從個專業嚟講咧，目前係未有一套咧，即係喺喺香港嚟講咧，我哋未有一套誒，即係嗰個誒標準嘅啊，即係粵拼啦。第二咧，我哋從個語言學習嘅角度咧，如果用粵拼嘅方法去學。
誒，跟住我哋有兩個動議咧，就需要係好短時間處理埋佢啦。分別就係阿毛孟靜議員提出嘅動議咧，同埋郭永興議員加埋曾之容議員和議嘅一個動議咧。睇到誒，直上大家都有個文本喺度㗎啦。如果大家冇乜特別反對嘅聲音嘅話咧，我就希望可以儘快噉樣處理咗佢誒，或者方便公眾。
敦促政府當局盡快完成中國語文課程第二語言學習架構檢討，為制定中文作為第二語言政策設下時間表。並應積極研究設立小學第二語言先導計劃。另外，政府應。
提供更多課程以外，學習中文的渠道，讓非華語學生有不同機會及平台學好中文，以全方位改善他們的聽講讀寫能力。係，我睇到唔到啲咩大嘅爭議。如果冇咩大問題嘅話，我哋就當呢個係我哋通過咗嘅動議啦，好嘛？咁冇人。
多謝主席。主席，本小組委員會促請教育局就本地少數族裔學生中文學習設立階段學習目標，令學生在一定階段後融入主流課課堂，並清晰地為教師提供從第二語言學生角度出發的學習領域課程。